I have a problem of procrastinating with everything I do.
저는 워낙 일을 할 때 뭐든지 뒤로 미루고 미루고 미루다가
I tend to put things off till the last minute.
마지막에 하는 성격이라 이게 문제가 되는데요.
It was more or less okay when I was in college.
대학교 때까지는 그게 어느 정도 됐는데
Now I started a work and step into a real life, I realize it is not good.
사회 초년생이다 보니까 제가 그것도 스스로 알고 잘못됐다는 것을 느끼고 하는데
My effort to change doesn't really work.
실제 노력을 하라고 하면 그게 잘 안 되고
Even the effort to change gets put off, so I feel rather lazy.
자꾸 그것도 미루다 보니까 제 스스로가 너무 나태한거 같아서
I feel the inner conflict about this.
그게 마음에서 충돌을 일으키고 있습니다. 이런걸 어떻게 해야 할까요.
Yes, you could just accept the loss.
네. 손해를 보면 되요.
You are still able to get along without the change. That is why you can't change.
지금은 손해를 봐도 살만하니까 안 고치고도 사는 거에요.
You think that you may lose something but
생각은 손해본다 하지만 마음 깊이 무의식 세계에서는
in your subconscious mind, you feel, "It's not that bad."
“그래도 뭐, 그래도 뭐” 이게 남아 있는거에요.
So, a person who can't quit smoking thinks that he should quit.
그러니까 담배를 피우던 사람이 담배 끊어야지 하면서도 못 끊는데,
He knows that it is bad for his health,
생각은 이거 해로운데 끊어야지 하지만,
but in his subconscious mind,
저 무의식 세계에서는
"smoking isn't going to kill me. Or what if I die!"
“담배 좀 피운다고 빨리 죽겠어? 또 죽으면 뭐 어때”
He rationalizes his smoking habit.
이런 식으로 자기를 합리화하는게 있다 이 말이에요.
This is because he has lived a long time with this habit.
그런 것처럼 그건 왜 그러냐하면 오래 살아온 습관 때문에 그래요.
It has become a habit.
습관화 되어 있기 때문에.
Procrastination has become your habit. Your habits control your mind.
미루는 것이 습관화 돼 버렸기 때문에, 습관화 되어 있는 것이 작용하는 게 마음이에요
It's not easy to change because it has become a habit.
이거는 쉽게 잘 안 변해요. 습관화된 거기 때문에요.
So, just live with this habit and accept the losses.
그러니까 그 정도의 습관은 놔 놓고 그냥 손해보면서 살면 되요
But, if you decide that the losses are too big, and are causing harm to you,
그런데 손해가 너무 커서 정말 이게 나한테 큰 피해다 하면
you must change no matter how old the habit is.
아무리 오래된 습관이라도 고쳐야하는 거에요.
No matter how long he has smoked, he needs to quit. But it will be difficult.
아무리 오래 피우던 담배라도 끊어야되고 고쳐야 되는거에요.
Have you finished college? (Questioner) Yes
대학 다녔어요? (질문자) 네
Then you should know.
그럼 알겠네.
Let's say, here is an object.
자 여기 물체가 있다고 하자 (물병을 단상 위에 놓으며)
What is the property of this object?
이 물체의 성질이 어떤게 있어요?
Among its properties, when an object is at rest, it continues to rest.
이 물체의 성질 중에 머무르고 있는 물체는 계속 머무르려고 하고,
when it is in motion, it continues to move.
움직이고 있는 물체는 계속 움직이려고 하는 성질이 있다 하는 거
Did you learn that in high school? (Questioner) Yes I did.
고등학교 때 배웠어요 안 배웠어요? (질문자) 배웠습니다
What is the law?
무슨 법칙이에요?
(Questioner) It's the law of inertia.
(질문자) 관성의 법칙입니다.
I guess you did go to high school. (Audience Laughter)
그래 고등학교 다니긴 다녔구나 (웃음)
It's the law of inertia.
관성의 법칙이에요.
An object at rest will remain at rest, and an object in motion continues in motion.
머무르고 있는 거는 계속 머물러 있으려 하고 움직이는 것은 계속 움직이려고 한다
This law of inertia applies to all things.
이게 모든 물체는 관성의 법칙이 있어요.
So, if you want to move an object at rest,
그렇기 때문에 이 머무르고 있는 물체를 움직이려고 하면
Do you need to apply force or will it move by itself?
저절로 움직여져요, 힘을 가해야돼요?
(Questioner) I have to apply force.
(질문자) 힘을 가해야합니다
To stop a moving object, will it stop by itself or should you apply force?
그럼 움직이고 있는 물체를 멈추려고 해도 저절로 돼요 힘을 가해야되요?
(Questioner) Apply force. (Sunim) Yes.
(질문자) 힘을 가해야됩니다 (스님) 힘을 가해야되죠.
Moving an object at rest or stopping one in motion,
머물고 있던 것이 움직인다든지, 움직이든 것이 멈춘다든지 하는 것은
means that the speed has changed.
속도가 변했다 이런 말이거든요
So, the force changes the speed, we call it acceleration, right?
그러면 가한 힘과 속도의 변화, 속도의 변화를 가속도라 그러잖아. 그렇죠?
What is the relationship between the applied force and acceleration?
이 가한 힘과 속도의 변화인 가속도는 어떤 관계에 있어요?
We express this as: F=MA, right?
그게 인제 우리가 F=MA 이렇게 쓰잖아?
This is the second law of motion: the law of acceleration.
이게 속도 가속도의 법칙이에요
So, the law of inertia is the first, the law of the acceleration is the second law
그러니까 관성의 법칙이 제 1법칙, 속도 가속도의 법칙이 제 2법칙,
The third law is action and reaction.
제 3법칙이 작용 반작용의 법칙
These are Newton's laws of motion, right?
이렇게 돼 있잖아요, 뉴튼의 법칙 중에, 그렇죠?
So, the law of inertia applies in our lives, too.
그러니까 우리들의 삶에 있어서도,
A smoker will continue to want to smoke.
내가 담배를 피웠다 그러면 담배를 피우는 사람은
In this case, the law of inertia applies to continuing-smoking
계속 피우고 싶은, 계속 피우려고 하는 관성의 법칙이 있다 이 말이에요.
The law of inertia is at work. You continue to procrastinate.
자기가 일을 미루면 계속 미루려고 하는 관성의 법칙이 있는 거에요.
So, if you want to stop something, what needs to happen?
그러니까 이 움직이고 있는 것을 멈추게 하려면 뭐가 가해져야한다고?
You have to apply force.
힘이 가해져야해요.
The force of wanting to quit needs to be applied.
그러니까 안 피우려고 하는 힘이 가해져야한다.
So, the force has to be applied to this object.
그런데 이 힘이 가해져야하는데, 이 정도 물체인데
If only a minor force is applied, will it move or not?
여기 힘을 조금 가하면 움직일까 안 움직일까?
It won't move even if you do it ten times.
열 번 해도 안 움직이겠지?
What needs to be done?
이걸 움직이려면 어떻게 해야한다?
You have to apply force that is greater than its frictional force.
이 마찰력보다 더 센 힘으로 가해줘야 되잖아
Can you apply it just once and let go, or do you continue applying the force?
그럼 가해주고 그냥 놔 버리면 될까 계속 가해야될까?
(Questioner) You have to continue
(질문자) 계속 해야죠
and the force needs to persist to move an object at rest.
그 힘이 지속 되어야, 멈춘 것이 움직이게 된다 이 말이에요.
So if you want to change your habit of procrastination,
그러니까 자기가 일을 미루려는 습관을 고치려고 하면
you need to have the determination strong enough to overcome the resistance.
그 미루는 저항을 이겨낼만한 각오가 처음에 세 있어야 하고,
And you need to persist in order to move away from procrastination.
두 번째는 그것이 지속되어져야 미루는 것을 안 미루는 쪽으로 움직여진다.
Let's say, here's some water.
만약에 여기 물이 있다.
If I insert a hose where it's higher and point it to lower,
내가 호스를 대서 이렇게 연결해 버리면 여기가 수면이 높고
the water should flow down naturally, right?
여기가 낮으니까 저절로 물이 내려오게 되잖아 그렇죠?
But it won't unless you siphon it.
그런데 저절로 내려와요? 가만 놔 놓으면 내려와요?
Why?
안 내려오지. 빨아줘야지. 왜 그럴까?
There is a barrier over the water surface so it can't flow over.
이 수면에 가려 있는 장막이 있으니까 못 넘어오는 거 아니야.
It will flow over only if you siphon it to go over the top.
그럼 호스를 대서 연결할 때는 빨아서 물이 요만큼 넘어가야 자동으로 넘어올거 아니야.
If you siphon it to come up only this high over and over,
그런데 빨아서 요까지 올라오다 내려가고 올라오다가 내려가고
even if you do it 300 times, will it flow over the top?
올라오다 내려가고 그러면 삼백번 빨아도 이게 넘어오나 안 넘어오나?
(Questioner) No, it won't. No, it won't. "Resolutions last 3 days."
(질문자) 안 넘어옵니다 안 넘어오지. 이게 작심삼일이란 말이야
To make the water flow over,
이걸 넘어오게 하려면 이 장벽 이상으로 넘겨줘야 이게 자동으로 넘어온단 말이야.
Do you understand?
무슨 말인지 아시겠어요?
So, you can just go on living as you are, just putting things off
그러니까 자기가 그냥 살든지, 미뤄가면서 그냥 살든지
and accept the consequences.
그래서 따르는 손해는 감수하고 살든지
In short, live according to your karma.
즉 현재의 업식을 그냥 갖고 살든지.
or, if you want to change, you have to fight against your own resistance.
만약에 고치려면 그 저항을 이겨내줘된다는 거야.
Up till now, you have tried a bit and stopped and tried and stopped,
자기는 그 저항을 조금 빨다가 놔 놓고 조금 빨다가 놔 놓고 이러니까
so your efforts have failed.
아무리 노력해도 안 되는거야.
You must exert greater effort and persist for a long while.
그러니까 세게 빨아야되고, 그걸 지속적으로 해야된다는 거야.
So, if you really want to overcome it, write it down.
그러니까 오늘부터 이걸 극복하겠다 그러면, 자기가 딱 쓰란 말이야.
Don't try to do it all at once.
앞으로 다 한꺼번에 하려고 하지 말고.
Regardless of what the work is, once you decide to do something, never postpone it.
어떤 회사 일이든 어떤 일 한 가지를 절대로 미루지 않는다고 정했으면
Even if you have to stay up all night, get it done.
밤을 새더라고 한단 말이야. 해 놓고 자는거야
If you continue in this fashion,
이렇게 지속적으로 한 달을 하고 백일을 하고 일년을 하면 습관이 바뀌게 되는 거에요.
Try that.
그렇게 하든지.
If you put your life on the line, you can overcome it.
그럴 때 죽을 각오까지 해 버리면 극복이 되요.
It's not working because you give up easily when it gets hard,
그런데 보통 하다가 좀 힘들면, 아이고 이렇게까지 해서 뭐하노 하면서
thinking, "Do I really have to work so hard at it?"
관둬버리고 관둬버리니까 안 되는 거에요
When Buddha sat under the bodhi tree,
그래서 부처님이 보리수 나무 밑에 앉을 때
he had an absolute resolve. "I am willing to die."
대결정심. 죽어도 좋다.
"I won't get up until I reach enlightenment, and I am willing to die for it."
내가 이것을 깨닫기 전에는 자리에서 일어나지 않겠다. 죽어도 좋다.
You need this kind of resolve to overcome your mara (hindrances).
이런 결정심을 해야 마장을 극복할 수 있다
A smoker wanting to quit, after a few days of trying,
담배를 피우다가 끊으려고 하는 사람이 그냥 처음에 며칠 안 피우면
his desire will increase to the point of getting physical pain.
피우고 싶은 욕망이 점점 증폭되어 몸이 아파
His pain will change his thinking.
몸이 아프면 사람이 의식이 바뀌어.
His reason for quitting was for his health, right?
담배 끊으려는 것은 몸이 건강하기 위해서 끊잖아. 그렇죠?
But, it defeats the purpose if it causes him physical pain.
그런데 이렇게 아프면 끊는 목적이 별로 없잖아.
So, he thinks that he'd be better off going back to smoke.
그러니까 이럴 바에야 피우는게 낫겠다.
When the pain gets worse, he thinks, "what's the point of quitting?"
그러다 더 심해지면, 이렇게까지 고통을 겪으면서 궂이 안 피워야되나.
"What's the point of living a long life? I should just smoke and die."
그렇게 오래살면 뭐 하나. 그냥 피우다 죽으면 되지.
His mind changes like this and rationalizes.
이렇게 의식이 자꾸 바뀐다는 거에요. 자기합리화.
Because, as I said before, there is a natural tendency of doing what it is doing.
왜냐하면 아까도 얘기했지만 작용하는 것은 계속 작용하려는 성질이 있기 때문에
So, this habit is hard to change. The resistance to change is strong.
이 업도 안 바뀌려고 해. 몸부림쳐. 저항을 한다는 말이에요.
So, he gives up by changing his mind in the end.
그렇게 해서 결국은 의식이 바뀌어버리면서 포기해버리는거야.
We tend to rationalize ourselves when we examine ourselves carefully.
늘 그렇게 자기가 자기를 살펴보면 자기합리화하는 작용이 있어.
We call it mara in our practice. The devil's obstruction so to speak.
이거를 우리가 수행할 때는 마장이다, 마구니다 이렇게 말해.
We don't mean it's evil. It just means it gets in our way of practice.
나쁜 놈이라는 뜻이 아니라 수행을 방해한다 이런 얘기에요.
It's not just you. It happens to everyone.
자기만 그런게 아니라 모든 사람이 다 그래.
So, we have saying: Resolutions last 3 days.
그래서 옛날부터 무슨 말이 있다? 작심삼일이라는 말이 있잖아, 그렇지?
Any habit that's formed at a young age is very hard to change.
그런데 이게 어릴 때 형성된 것은 진짜 바꾸기 어려워.
That's why we say, "You can't change your inborn nature".
그래서 천성은 못 고친다, 이런 말도 있고,
Or, when someone does change, we say, "He's going to die soon".
천성이 변하면 죽을 때가 다 됐다, 이런 말도 있고.
These show how difficult it is to change.
그 말은 그만큼 바뀌기가 어렵다
Since it's that difficult, what did people say in the old days?
이게 바뀌기가 어렵다 보니 옛날에는 무슨 말이 있다?
It's your destiny, people used to say.
운명이다. 이런 말이 있는거에요.
"God made you this way"
그건 네가 하느님이 이렇게 살라고 정했다,
"It's from your past life; it's your destiny."
전생에 네가 그걸 타고 났다, 사주팔자에 타고났다.
It shows how difficult it is to change.
그거는 그만큼 바뀌기 어렵다 이 얘기에요.
But Buddha said: All is impermanent. There is nothing that does not change.
그러나 부처님이 '제행무상이다' 이런 말은 바뀌지 않는 것은 아무것도 없다.
Only, it is hard to change.
다만 그것이 바뀌기 어렵지.
Human beings lack the willpower to change
인간의 의지가 그걸 바꿀만큼 강하지 못하기 때문에
so we say things like that.
그냥 못 바꾸나보다 이렇게 생각한 거에요.
Buddha was the first to break through it.
그것을 최초로 돌파한 사람이 부처님이란 말이에요.
So don't assume that it's hard to change your little habit.
그러니까 여러분들이 그런 습관하나 바꾸는 것은 어렵다고 생각하면 안 돼.
If you really want to change, do it with a strong resolve.
정말 바꾸고 싶으면 딱 결심을 하고 자기가 해야되고
The reason I told you to stay the way you are was
스님이 그냥 살아라 하는 것은, 그렇게 안 하려면,
because if you try and quit, try and quit you will end up tormenting yourself.
괜히 시도하고 관두고 시도하고 관두고 시도하고 관두면 나중에 자학증세가 생겨.
You will torture yourself thinking you are a worthless person.
나는 진짜 형편없는 인간이구나 이렇게 자기를 학대한다 이 말이야.
In that case, it's better to go on as you are.
그럴 바에야 그냥 생긴대로 사는게 낫다. 아시겠어요?
(Questioner) Thank you. (Audience Applause)
(질문자) 알겠습니다. 감사합니다. (청중) 박수
No...hold the microphone, So what will you do?
아니 마이크 가지고 있어봐. 그래 자기는 어떡할래요?
After listening to me, did you decide to change or stay the way you are?
바꾸기로 했어요 생긴대로 살기로 했어요? 스님 얘기들으면서.
I will try to change.
저는 바꾸도록 노력하겠습니다
When you're trying to change, don't say things like,"It's no use."
바꾸려고 노력할 때는 하다가 안 되더라 그런 소리 하면 안 돼
You must tackle it with your willingness to die for it.
죽을 각오를 하고 덤벼야한다 이 말이야
In order to change, you may stay up all night or could get sick the next day.
이걸 바꾸려면 밤샘도 해야되고 이러면 이틑날 몸이 아프고 이런 일도 생겨
I go around giving 300 scheduled lectures these days.
스님도 지금 300강 다니잖아.
Do you think I always feel well or sometimes I get sick?
그러면 늘 건강할까 아픈 날도 있을까?
There are days when I am sick…
아픈 날도 있고 죽을 거 같기도 하고
There are days I feel like I'm dying. Sometimes I really want to take a day off.
오늘 하루는 정말 쉬어야되겠다 싶은 생각이 들 때도 있고 그래.
But, since I promised, I do it even if I might collapse and die.
그러나 하기로 했으면 쓰러져서 죽으면 죽고.
I overcome the mara by thinking that
'법문하러 다니다 죽으면 영광스러운 일이다' 이렇게 생각을 해야 마장이 벗어나지.
Otherwise, I would quit in the middle of it.
안 그러면 중간에 다 그만두게 돼.
So, when you make a decision to do something, just do it.
그러니까 자기가 어떤 일을 하기로 했으면 그냥 하는거지,
Don't make excuses of any kind. Otherwise, your habit will hinder you.
자꾸 이런저런 핑계를 대면 아까 얘기한대로 습관이 장애를 하는거야.
There are two ways to overcome your habit.
자기는 내일부터 그걸 극복하는 방법은 두 가지
A long term plan is for you to get up at 5 a.m. every morning and pray.
장기전이 있는데 그건 뭐냐면 매일 아침에 5시에 일어나서 한 시간 기도를 해.
Would it be easy or hard?
그러면 쉬울까 어려울까?
(Questioner) It would be hard.
(질문자) 어렵습니다
Which would be easier? Doing that or changing your habit?
그게 쉬울까 습관 고치는게 쉬울까?
Get into the habit of getting up at 5:00 every morning to pray.
그래서 매일 아침에 5시에 일어나서 기도하는 습관을 아파도 하고 비와도 하고
If you can do that, you can change other things about yourself, too.
그러면 그게 유지되면 다른거까지 고쳐져.
If it's too hard and you are skipping, there is another way.
두 번째 그것도 해 보니 또 빼먹고 안 되고, 108배가 힘들다
Take three days off and come to the temple and do 10,000 bows.
그러면 언제 절에 와서 삼일 휴가를 내고 와서 만배를 해 버리면 돼.
After the 10,000 bows, 108 bows will be easy, right?
만배를 딱 하고 나면 108배는 쉬울까 어려울까?
(Questioner) It would be easy. Very easy.
(질문자) 쉽습니다 아주 쉬워요.
Your hinderance will disappear while you're doing the 10,000 prostrations.
그러면 이 장애가 만배하는 동안에 나머지 장애가 없어져버려.
Are you willing to take on this challenge to change your habit, or not? You are not.
그렇게 자기가 도전, 그렇게라도 해서 고쳐보겠다 생각을 하나 안 하나?
That is why you can't change.
안 하지. 그러니까 못 고쳐지는거야.
So, starting tomorrow morning, get up at 5 a.m. and do 108 prostrations.
그러니까 오늘 가서 내일 아침부터 5시에 일어나서 뭐 한다? 108배 기도한다.
What if you went to bed at 4 a.m.?
그리고 4시에 자면 어떻게 하느냐.
You still get up at 5 and do the bows even if you go back to sleep afterwards.
그때도 5시에 일어나서 기도하고 또 자더라도 무조건 정해놓은 시간에는 하는 거에요.
Understand?
아시겠어요? (질문자) 알겠습니다.
If you can't keep this up, come to the temple and do the 10,000 prostrations.
몇 번 시도해보고 약속이 잘 안 지켜지면 주말에 보따리 싸 들고 절에 와서 만 배를 한다.
Even if you feel like dying, just do it. You will really feel like dying.
죽을 것 같아도 그냥 하는거에요.
So, bow down and see you're dead. If you're not dead, then get up.
그러면 하는 방법은 일단 엎드려 보고 죽었나 안 죽었나 보고.
If you're not dead standing, bow down again.
안 죽었으면 일어나고. 일어나서 안 죽었으면 또 엎드리고.
If you are willing to die, you can do this.
죽을 각오를 하면 그렇게 하면 되잖아.
Then eventually, you would have finished 10,000 bows. Okay?
그러면 시간이 흐르면 만 배가 되는 거에요. 알았죠?
That's how you overcome yourself.
그렇게 해서 자기를 극복하려면 그렇게 해야 극복이 되지.
If not, as a young man, why would you go on living as you do now?
안 그러면 지금 젊은 날에 계속 그런식으로 해서 어떻게 하겠어.
(Questioner) Thank you.
(잘문자) 감사합니다